Josh C Bongard

Summary Curriculum Vitae

E428 Innovation Hall
University of Vermont, Burlington, VT 05405
jbongard.github.io
www.meclab.org
@DoctorJosh
josh.bongard@uvm.edu
Google Scholar. 9368 citations. H-index: 45.

RESEARCH STATEMENT

There are two main thrusts in my research group: evolutionary robotics and machine science.

In **evolutionary robotics**, we take a holistic approach to robotics. We teach an AI to design robots "from the ground up" to best be able to perform some desired task. The AI does so by determining where to put motors, sensors, what shape the robot should have, what materials it should constructed from, and how it should be controlled by a neural network. Only this last aspect of a robot's design is covered by traditional AI approaches. Most recently, we have adapted this method to create the world's first computer-designed organisms (the "xenobots"): living robots made from biological tissues, rather than technological components.

In machine science, we attempt to automate all aspects of the scientific method. This process usually involves five steps. 1. A "scientist AI" generates hypotheses about how some system works (e.g. how cells communicate to stabilize after surprise). 2. An "engineer AI" then dreams up how best to poke the system of interest, or build some interesting version of that system, to test that hypothesis (e.g. a mm-sized robot built from frog tissue). 3. A "robot scientist" then carries out that intervention, or builds that system variant. 4. The robot's success or failure is fed back to the scientist AI, leading it to revise its hypothesis. 5. This process is repeated until the AIs and robot scientist make a new discovery. Often, this discovery is different or beyond what human scientists may have been capable of imagining.

APPOINTMENTS

- 2015 Cyril G. Veinott Green and Gold Professor, Department of Computer Science, College of Engineering & Mathematical Sciences, University of Vermont
- 2015–2019 Director, Vermont Advanced Computing Core, UVM's high performance computing facility.
 - 2014 Secondary appointment in the School of Engineering, UVM
 - 2013 Secondary appointment in the Neuroscience Graduate Program, UVM
 - 2006– Director, Morphology, Evolution & Cognition Laboratory
- 2003–2006 **Postdoctoral Associate**, Cornell University

Advisor: Hod Lipson, Director of the Creative Machines Laboratory

EDUCATION

1999–2003 **Ph.D.**, Department of Informatics, University of Zurich, Switzerland

Incremental Approaches to the Combined Evolution of a Robot's Body and Brain.

Advisor: Polf Pfaifar, Director of the Zurich Artificial Intelligence Laboratory

Advisor: Rolf Pfeifer, Director of the Zurich Artificial Intelligence Laboratory

1998–1999 M.S., Evolutionary & Adaptive Systems, University of Sussex, UK

1993–1997 **B.Sc.**, Honors Computer Science, McMaster University, Canada (graduated *Summa Cum Laude*)

Books

1. Pfeifer, R. and J. Bongard (2006)

How the Body Shapes the Way We Think: A New View of Intelligence,

Boston, MA: MIT Press. (Translated into Chinese, Japanese, Arabic and an E-book)

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

1. S Kriegman, D Blackiston, M Levin, J Bongard (2021)

Kinematic self-replication in reconfigurable organisms.

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 118(49): e2112672118.

2. D Blackiston, E Lederer, S Kriegman, S Garnier, J Bongard, M Levin (2021) A cellular platform for the development of synthetic living machines.

Science Robotics, 6(52).

3. JC Bongard & M Levin (2021)

Living things are not (20th century) machines.

Frontiers in Ecology and Evolution, https://doi.org/10.3389/fevo.2021.650726

4. S Kriegman, D Blackiston, M Levin, J Bongard. (2020).

A scalable pipeline for the design of reconfigurable organisms.

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 117(4): 1853-1859.

 I Rahwan, M Cebrian, N Obradovich, J Bongard, J-F Bonnefon, C Breazeal, JW Crandall, NA Christakis, ID Couzin, MO Jackson, NR Jennings, E Kamar, IM Kloumann, H Larochelle, D Lazer, R McElreath, A Mislove, DC Parkes, A Pentland, ME Roberts, A Shariff, JB Tenenbaum & M Wellman (2019). Machine behavior.

Nature, 568: 477-486

6. Bongard, J. C. (2011)

Morphological change in machines accelerates the evolution of robust behavior.

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 108(4): 1234-1239.

7. Bongard, J. and H. Lipson (2007)

Automated reverse engineering of nonlinear dynamical systems.

Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 104(24): 9943-9948.

8. Bongard, J., V. Zykov and H. Lipson (2006)

Resilient machines through continuous self-modeling.

Science, 314: 1118-1121.

SELECTED MEDIA COVERAGE _

Dec, 2021 Stephen Colbert

CNN, BBC, CNBC, Science Friday, Forbes, NPR, New Scientist, The Times, Bloomberg, & 100s more.

Jan, 2020 CNN

Nov, 2006 "Injured Robot Learns to Limp" Nature News

"New Robot Shrugs Off Injury" Science News

"Robotic Recovery" MIT Technology Review

"Self-Aware Robots" Discovery Channel

SELECTED	AWARDS
2021	The National Academy of Sciences' Cozzarelli Prize. (Announcement video.)
2020	Xenobots nominated for The Design Museum's Beazley Design of the Year PNAS paper reporting xenobots in Altmetric's Top 100 for 2020.
2014	National STEM Innovation Award (awarded by the Concept Schools)
2010	Presidential Early Career Award for Scientists and Engineers (PECASE). [Photo with Obama] NSF CAREER award.
2007	One of <i>MIT Technology Review</i> 's TR35: Top 35 Young Innovators Under 35 Microsoft New Faculty Fellowship